# 福建 泉州
(Quanzhou, Fujian)
# （前方有吃的）
(Food available ahead)
# （康庄 满煎糕）
(Kangzhuang "manjiangao" pancake)
# 阿姨 我问下半片就是半个是吧
Auntie, what does "half piece" mean? Half sized order?
# （价格表）
# 半片10块钱
(price table)
10 yuan for half a piece.
# 这样的是半片吗
Is this what you call "half a piece"?
# （这样的半片）10块钱
10 yuan (for half a piece like this).
# 哦 都一样是吧
Oh... All at the same price?
# 有不一样的
Not all.
# 看你要加...
It depends on...
# （冬瓜 花生 半片10元）
# 冬瓜、花生还是不加的
(With wintermelon/peanut: 10 yuan)
if you want to add wintermelon, peanut or not.
# 都需要切开是吧
All are sliced, are they?
# （普通版：半片8元）
# 都是切开的啊
(Plain version: 8 yuan)
Yeah, all are sliced.
# 给我拿半片升级版的
I'd like half a piece of the upgraded version.
# 10块钱的
The 10 yuan version.
# （升级版 10元半片）
(Upgraded version with wintermelon/peanut: 10 yuan)
# 半片哦
Half a piece?
# 对
Yeah.
# 这半片给你
This half is for you.
# 过去了
Paid.
# 他们这边正在做（满煎糕）
They are cooking ("manjiangao" pancakes) over there.
# 加了冬瓜糖
With wintermelon sugar added.
# （加料：冬瓜、花生、芝麻）
(Added ingredients: wintermelon, peanut, sesame)
# （焖 不至于火候太大）
(Simmering to avoid overcooking)
# 差不多熟的时候
When it's almost done.
# 拿起来焖一下
simmer it for a while.
# 我做这个也不久
I haven't been doing this for very long.
# 差不多40年
Just almost 40 years.
# （40年！）
(40 years!)
# 人家有的是100年了
Some others have been doing this for 100 years.
# 三代人了
By three generations of people.
# 我比人家做的时间少
My career is much shorter than theirs.
# 这个锅很重
This cooker is very heavy.
# 差不多要40斤
Almost 40 jin (= 20kg).
# 薄的铁锅不行
Thin iron cookers don't work.
# 用薄的会...会...
Thin ones will, will...
# （当地方言）
(words in local dialect)
# 烧焦
will burn (the cake).
# 你可以自己拿一下
You may try lifting it.
# 试试看
Have a try.
# 真的不轻
Not a light one.
# 真的挺重
Really heavy.
# 得从早上拿到中午
Gotta keep lifting it from morning all the way till noon.
# 不是一下子就完了
Not a one-shot work.
# 一直做到中午？
All the way till noon?
# 一直做到中午
All the way till noon.
# 不是拿一个就没有了
It's not like, you lift it once and it's done.
# 每天就要这么提着
It's like... Have to lift it like this everyday.
# 主要是要把锅提到前面去
Mainly, you need to move the cooker to the front.
# 你要拿到前面去
You need to move it to the front,
# 拿到火上去啊
move it to above the flame.
# 逛西街...
We are...
# 逛西街真的是逛累了
We are now quite exhausted walking this "Xijie" street.
# 这个满煎糕已经成为不完整的了
This "manjiangao" pancake is no longer in its whole.
# 虽然说咱只是买了10元半片的
Though we only bought this half a piece for 10 yuan.
# 它这种满煎糕
This manjiangao
# 很像加了红糖的发糕
looks like a "fagao" (leavened rice cake) with brown sugar added.
# 连外形也像
Even the shape looks like that.
# 这个满煎糕因为煎烤的原因
Since the manjiangao has been baked,
# 所以你看它的外皮
if you look at its skin,
# 是发暗褐色的
it's in dark brown.
# 像铜锣烧一样
Like a dorayaki.
# 因为是发酵的原因
Since it's leavened,
# 它这个是比较蓬松的
it's kind of puffy.
# 你一捏还会回弹 回弹 回弹
If you pinch it, it bounces, bounces and bounces.
# 咱们要的是升级版的
As we ordered an upgraded one,
# 里面不仅有这个...
it contains not only...
# 冬瓜糖 红糖
wintermelon sugar and brown sugar,
# 还加了这个花生
there's also peanut,
# 还有这个芝麻
and also sesame.
# 这个真的是很蓬松 蓬软
It's really puffy and soft.
# 看
Look!
# 你轻轻一捏
Pinch it like this.
# 它其实很像这种蛋糕的质地
The texture is similar to a cake.
# 可能是...
Except, probably...
# 就少了鸡蛋
Eggs only.
# 尝一口
Let me try.
# 中间是馅
Inside is the stuffing.
# 周围是面
Around that is the cake.
# 满煎糕吃起来就是蓬松 柔软
The mouthfeel is puffy and soft,
# 带有的甜味是红糖的甜味
with the sweetness of brown sugar.
# 所以说你不会觉得齁
So it's not cloying.
# 还有就是这个花生碎在里面
Together with the ground peanut,
# 增加了坚果的嚼头和香气
it gets the extra nutty chewiness and aroma.
# 我去买东西的时候
When I was ordering,
# 叔叔很有意思
the uncle was pretty interesting.
# 我说叔叔阿姨你们做多久了
I said, "uncle and auntie, how long have you been working on this".
# 叔叔说干的时间也不长
Uncle said "not very long".
# 也就是40年
"Just 40 years"
# 对 这一个满煎糕的小店
Yeah. This tiny manjiangao shop
# 藏在巷子里
has been hiding in the alley
# 40年了
for 40 years.
# 休息时间不就是过年那几天（过年是7天）
Days off... Days off are those days in Chinese new year (7 days).
# 如果那几天不是就好了嘛
Those few days are good.
# 几十年如一日
(We've been working for) decades as the first day.
# 这才是最难的
That's the most difficult part.
# （几十年如一日 这才是最难的）
(Decades as the first day. That's the most difficult part)
# （关注 雪鱼探店）
(Subscribe)